Guide to the Henry Nathaniel Oakes papers, 1904-1974
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Henry Nathaniel Oakes papers 1904-1974
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Oakes, Henry Nathaniel, 1935-
9.5 linear feet Extent: Approx. 5000 Items
Henry Nathaniel Oakes was a minister from North Carolina; he received his Ph.D. from the University of Iowa in 1974. Collection consists of research material for and drafts of Oakes's Ph.D. dissertation, which focuses on the career of Robert Elijah Jones (1872—1960), the first African American elected to the episcopacy in the former Methodist Episcopal Church (1920). Oakes's materials document the relationship between Jones and his close friend Booker T. Washington, Jones's accomodationist approach to racial integration, as well as the black struggle for equality in the predominantly white Methodist Episcopal Church in the first half of the twentieth century. Among Oakes's research papers are many folders of typed notes excerpting and commenting on Jones's statements made from 1905 to 1920 on abolition, African American business, mob violence and lynching, education, and politics. Acquired as part of the John Hope Franklin Research Center for African and African American History and Culture at Duke University.
RL.00967
Language: Material in English
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is closed pending processing.
Collection may contain materials to which the Acknowledgment of Legal Responsibilities and Privacy Rights form applies. Patrons must sign this form before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. Consequently, there may be a 24-hour delay in obtaining these materials.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Henry Nathaniel Oakes papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 2003.
Collection Overview
The papers of Henry Nathaniel Oakes chiefly consist of research material for and drafts of Oakes's 1973 Ph.D. dissertation, which focuses on the career of Robert Elijah Jones (1872—1960), the first African American Bishop of the Methodist Episcopal Church, elected in 1920. Jones was born in Greensboro, North Carolina. Oakes's materials document the relationship between Jones and his close friend Booker T. Washington, Jones's accomodationist approach to racial integration, as well as the black struggle for equality in the predominantly white Methodist Episcopal Church in the first half of the twentieth century.
The earliest dates (1904-1940s) derive from photocopied research materials pertaining to the period during which Robert Jones was active, chiefly from Methodist publications, including reports, newsclippings, articles, and correspondence. These materials contain exceprts and notes on comments Jones made from 1905 to 1920 on abolition, African American business, mob violence and lynching, education, and politics. Also among the research papers are typed notes Henry Oakes took on an unidentified work by Robert E. Jones. Typewritten notes are typically annotated with many hand-written comments and underlined passages. Handwritten notes are often found on the backs of re-used elementary school worksheets.
Additional materials in the collection include University of Iowa forms and policies; correspondence between Oakes and members of the Jones family and Univ. of Iowa faculty; a set of typed transcripts of six or seven interviews conducted by Oakes with Jones family members, ministers, and other individuals; a set of black-and-white photographs of Jones, his immediate family, and Church officials; and five microfilm reels.
Mold remediation has been carried out by Conservation staff on selected portions of the collection. To facilitate access to severely damaged items, photocopies are available for use and are housed alongside the originals.
Acquired as part of the John Hope Franklin Research Center for African and African American History and Culture.
Subject Headings
Jones, Robert Elijah, 1872-1960; Oakes, Henry Nathaniel, 1935-; Methodist Church (U.S.) -- History; Methodist Church (U.S.). Central Jurisdiction -- History; United Methodist Church (U.S.) -- History -- 20th century; African American Methodists -- History -- 20th century; African Americans -- Civil rights -- History -- 20th century; African Americans -- Segregation -- History -- 20th century; African Americans -- Southern States; Race relations -- Religious aspects -- Christianity; Racism -- Religious aspects -- History -- 20th century; Segregation -- United States; North Carolina -- History; Southern States -- History; Black-and-white photographs; Microfilms; Negatives; John Hope Franklin Research Center for African and African American History and Culture
Contents of Collection
- Henry N. Oakes papers, 1904-1974 and undated, (13 boxes)
  Collection is arranged in original order as received; the majority is accessible, but some materials may need further processing before contents can be accessed. Some oversize material has been rehoused for preservation purposes.
  Collection is closed pending processing; please consult with a reference archivist for access to this collection.
  - Typed dissertation draft (Box 1)
  - Dissertation prospectus (Box 2)
  - Handwritten notes; typed excerpts from Jones's writings and speeches; typed drafts (Box 2)
  - Enlargement photocopies of newspaper articles on Jones or by Jones, 1910s (Box 3)
    Chiefly from the Southwestern Christian Advocate, for which Jones served as editor.
  - Sections of handwritten and typed drafts (Box 4)
  - Set of typed transcripts from six or seven interviews Oakes conducted with individuals affiliated or related to Jones, 1970s (Box 4)
  - Research materials, several folders (Box 4)
  - Photocopied primary research materials (Box 5)
  - Handwritten notes, outlines (Box 5)
  - Draft of thesis (final version?) (Box 5)
  - Handwritten drafts with extensive edits, pasted-in sections (Box 6)
  - Handwritten and typed research and planning notes (Box 6)
  - Correspondence to individuals for research purposes and interviews (Box 6)
  - University of Iowa handbook and forms (Box 6)
  - Handwritten drafts with extensive edits, pasted-in sections (Box 7)
  - Correspondence from Jones family, 1971, 1974, (2 items) (Box 7)
  - Typed dissertation draft (complete?) (Box 7)
  - Various notes for dissertation, (2 folders) (Box 8)
  - An Era in Methodist History Closes, 1960 [photocopy] (Box 8)
    Editorial on the occasion of Jones's death in 1960 (and the 40th anniversary of his election to the Church episcopacy).
  - Oversize clippings of articles about amendment to elect African American bishop, 1907-1912, (2 folders) (photocopies) (Box 8)
    Southwestern Christian Advocate, underlined by Oakes, on African Americans and the episcopacy.
  - Oversize clippings from Southwestern Christian Advocate, 1907-1910, (photocopies) (Box 8)
    Some clippings concern equal accommodation on rail cars.
  - Oversize clippings from Southwestern Christian Advocate, 1907-1910, (photocopies) (Box 8)
    Clippings concern the characteristics of African Americans: hard work, perseverance, etc.
  - Five reels of microfilmed research materials (Box 9)
  - Photocopied research materials (Box 9)
  - Handwritten and typed research notes (Box 9)
  - Correspondence with Univ. of Iowa faculty and thesis committee, Jones family, and others (Box 9)
    Includes letters referring to a Jones family member's objections to Oakes's conclusion that Jones favored an accomodationist approach.
  - Photographs of Jones, his immediate family, and Methodist Church officials, 1910s-1930s [black-and-white reproductions; negatives included], (approx. 40 items) (Box 9)
  - Typed copies of dissertation, several sets? (Box 10-12)
  - The Circuit Rider Dismounts, by H.D. Tarish, 1938 (Box 13)
    Typed and revised draft.
  - Robert E. Jones research materials from Methodist publishing house library, 1910-1930 [photocopies] (Box 13)
  - Materials from General Conference Journals and Daily Christian Advocate, 1904-1940, (3 folders) (photocopies) (Box 13)
    Underlined and annotated by Oakes.
  - Notes for dissertation on Jones, unification, and for conclusion of dissertation, 1936-1970s (Box 13)
  - Notes from Robert E. Jones: two items, 1905-1919 (Box 13)
    Opposition to mob violence and lynching; Comments from Southwestern [Methodist Conference] on Negro business.
  - Robert E. Jones research materials: Jones's comments on education from Southwestern [Methodist Conference], 1905-1919 [photocopies] (Box 13)
  - Notes on dissertation by Joseph Anthony Perez on unification of Methodist black and white churches (1964), undated [photocopies] (Box 13)
  - Numerical calculations for black conferences membership (Methodist?), 1904-1939 (Box 13)
  - Robert E. Jones research materials: Jones advocates and supports inter-racial cooperation..., 1908-1920 [photocopies] (Box 13)
    Typed title at top of page: Jones advocates and supports inter-racial cooperation as the way to overcome hostility, promote understanding, gain rights.
  - Robert E. Jones research materials: Jones's attitude to Theodore Roosevelt, 1905-1919 [photocopies] (Box 13)
  - Robert E. Jones research materials: Changes, if any, after the death of Washington, 1913-1919 [photocopies] (Box 13)
  - Robert E. Jones research materials: Jones's attitude towards agitation as a means to gain rights, instead counsels patience, 1905-1919 [photocopies] (Box 13)
  - Quotes and notes on Robert E. Jones: Jones's complaints against and efforts against Jim Crow railroad accommodations, 1905-1920 [photocopies] (Box 13)